"Medicine’s Response to the Changing Science on Fluoride Safety"
The National Toxicology Program
is part of the
Public Health Service,
in partnership with
the CDC, FDA, and NIH,
dedicated to the analysis
of agents of concern
to identify any toxic effects.
How did the medical community
respond to the draft conclusions
in their recent systematic
review that concluded that
fluoride is to be presumed to be
a cognitive neurodevelopmental
hazard to humans,
based on studies
showing lower IQ scores
among kids with
higher fluoride exposure?
What do you do
when current research
contradicts public practices,
when new evidence doesn't
conform with existing beliefs?
Well, health authorities
have continued to conclude
that fluoride is
unequivocally safe,
despite the new studies
in recent years
linking fluoride
exposure in pregnancy
with adverse effects
on fetal brain development.
There are still papers
on how to "sell"
fluoridation
of the water supply,
targeting social media
and the person-to-person spread
of fluoride "misinformation."
Search engines are to be
encouraged, at the very least,
to flag search engine results
that point to water fluoridation
health "misinformation"
suggesting adverse effects.
In promoting support for
community water fluoridation,
maybe we don't even want
to proclaim its safety
for fear of raising
questions about risks.
I mean, if you're
saying it's safe,
then that begs the question,
"Well, is it not safe?"
Maybe we shouldn't even
talk about whether it's safe.
The tendency
to ignore new evidence
that does not conform
to widespread beliefs
may be impeding
our response to early warnings
about fluoride as a potential
developmental neurotoxin,
but some are just so
fixed in their views
on fluoridation that they
won't reassess their stance
no matter what
the latest research might show.
Ironically, it was
the antifluoridationists
who were accused of their
"anti-scientific attitudes,"
but now it's the
pro-fluoridationists.
One of the most facile
pro-fluoridation arguments
I ran across is the suggestion
that fluoride
can't be hurting IQs,
because over the last
half century of fluoridation,
IQ scores have been going up
rather than down.
The jaw-dropping irony is that
a substantial part
of that rise may have been due
to the removal of another
neurotoxic element, lead.
It's worth remembering
that the science surrounding
the neurodevelopmental hazard
of low-level lead exposure
was also bitterly contested
using the same kinds
of arguments we see today
in the fluoridation debate.
A few short years
before leaded gas
was effectively banned
in the United States,
a meta-analysis of
lead exposure and child IQ
only found 24 human studies,
all cross-sectional,
with a typical associated
loss in intelligence
of about four IQ points.
The current data suggest
a similar IQ loss from fluoride
from an even stronger
body of evidence.
A spokesperson for
the American Dental Association
responded to the new data
by pointing out
that some cities that
have ended water fluoridation
saw an increase in cavities.
Okay, but that's kind
of a strange response
to data suggesting the potential
for permanent brain damage
in children.
I mean, I know they are
the dental association,
but how could they so easily
ignore the serious red flags
of potential neurotoxicity
for cavity reduction?
This is not to say tooth decay
isn't a serious health issue,
but there are ways to get the
cavity-preventing benefits
of fluoride without the risks.
Since the primary benefits arise
from topical contact
with our enamel,
but the primary risks arise
from systemic absorption,
we can follow Europe's example
and safely reap the rewards
using fluoride toothpaste
and mouthwashes.
In Europe, 98 percent
of the population
drink unfluoridated water.
Several countries,
including France, Germany,
the Netherlands, Denmark,
Sweden, banned fluoridation
decades ago in favor
of fluoride toothpaste,
as more than ten years ago,
the official scientific
committee on health risks
of the European Union concluded
that topical application
of fluoride is most effective
in preventing tooth decay
and that there appears to be
no obvious advantage
in favor of fluoridating
the water supply.